<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A continuation of all the principall occurrences which hath happened to the Leaguers lying before Breda shewing into what great extreamity and necessity the armie of the Marquesse Spinola is likely to fall into for want of prouision and pay: for which causes he hath already lost aboue 12000 men. With a relation of the forces that are now a leauying vnder, and for the command of Count Mansfield, and the Duke of Brunswicke, by Collonell Smith, and Captaine Daniel de la Riue, with expectation to receiue the forces now dismist by the Kings of Denmarke and Sweden, intending to aduenture their fortunes once more together. ...</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1625</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 24 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08151</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18507.354</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116918</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852133</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852133</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17440</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08151)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17440)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1128:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A continuation of all the principall occurrences which hath happened to the Leaguers lying before Breda shewing into what great extreamity and necessity the armie of the Marquesse Spinola is likely to fall into for want of prouision and pay: for which causes he hath already lost aboue 12000 men. With a relation of the forces that are now a leauying vnder, and for the command of Count Mansfield, and the Duke of Brunswicke, by Collonell Smith, and Captaine Daniel de la Riue, with expectation to receiue the forces now dismist by the Kings of Denmarke and Sweden, intending to aduenture their fortunes once more together. ...</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 17, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By B. A[lsop] for Thomas Archer, and are to be solde at his shop in Popes head Alley, ouer against the signe of the Horse-shooe,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1625.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Now = Newsbooks 354.</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 3594.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 3594 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Thirty Years' War, 1618-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Breda (Netherlands) --  History --  Siege, 1624-1625 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17440:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17440:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A CONTINVATION OF ALL THE PRINCIPALL OC<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currences which hath happened to the Leaguers lying before <hi>Breda,</hi> ſhewing into what great extrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity and neceſſity the Armie of the Marqueſſe <hi>Spinola</hi> is likely to fall into for want of prouiſion and pay: for which cauſes he hath already loſt aboue 12000 Men. With a relation of the Forces that are now a leauy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vnder, and for the command of <hi>Count Mansfield,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Brunſwicke,</hi> by Collonell <hi>Smith,</hi> and Captaine <hi>Daniel de la Riue,</hi> with expectation to receiue the Forces now diſmiſt by the Kings of <hi>Denmarke</hi> and <hi>Sweden,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to aduenture their fortunes once more together. The reſolutions both of the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and the States of the vnited Prouinces, for the ſudden leuying of two great Armies more, to bring into the Field againſt each other, with the great ſtraite the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> is lately <hi>put to for want of Shipping and Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and what hinderance it is to his preſent affaires.</hi> Likewiſe herein is related the laſt proceedings of all Chriſtendome.</p>
            <p>Printed at <hi>London</hi> by <hi>B. A.</hi> for THOMAS ARCHER, and are to be ſolde at his ſhop in Popes head Alley, ouer againſt the ſigne of the Horſe-ſhooe, 1625.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:17440:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:17440:2"/>
            <div type="part">
               <head>From Vienna the 2. of October.</head>
               <p>THe inuaſion which the Turkes made lately in Hungarie is confirmed againe with the laſt letters that came out of the ſame Kingdome, from whence they write likewiſe thoſe particulars, namely: how that they haue fired ſeuerall villages, and defeated many Imperiall ſouldiers, and almoſt the whole regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lord <hi>Palſy:</hi> that there were many Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garians reuolted, and would ſticke to <hi>Bethlem Gabor,</hi> who is preparing a great Armie to ſet vpon ſome of the Emperours dominions: That <hi>Bethlem Gabor</hi> had inuited to his wedding, with the daughter of the Lord <hi>George Setſdhi,</hi> many of the Lords and States of Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garie, and made great preparation to come downe with many Noblemen and Courtiers.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>From <hi>Vienna</hi> the 2. of October.</head>
               <p>To day arriued here the Chancelor of <hi>Bethlem Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor,</hi> and brought ſome horſe and other preſents with him to beſtow vpon the Emperour as it is rumored. But for all this, wee cannot conceiue any hope that <hi>Bethlem Gabor</hi> will make a peaceable end with the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, ſeeing that he leauieth dayly more and more ſouldiers.</p>
               <p>And for as much as concerneth the treatie of peace with the Turkes, wee cannot beleeue that it will take
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:17440:3"/> any good ſucceſſe, ſeeing that they make many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rodes vpon the Emperours dominions, and compaſſed lately with their horſe, Nouigrad, Setſhin and Palam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ha. And wee haue here tidings how that the Turkes are reſolued to pitch a campe betwixt Offen and Newhenſel, and that <hi>Bethlem Gabor</hi> is marching vp with many thouſands of men.</p>
               <p>A Commiſſion or Patent being lately ſent into the land of Ens to depoſe all the Proteſtant Preachers which are there, the States of the land offered to pay to the Duke the twelue<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> hundred thouſand Florins (which hee is pretending from the Emperour for his warlike expenſes, and keepeth the land of Ens as a morgage or pawne) if they might conti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e there with the free exerciſe of the Religion as they did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>From <hi>Prague</hi> the 12. of October.</head>
               <p>The Horſe of the Duke of Holſtayn which were lately diſmiſt, are now againe taken in the ſeruice of the Emperour, and getnew Cornets ſeeing they rent the other from their Lances as ſoone a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they were diſmiſt: and it is rumored that they ſhall be ſent into Hungarie angainſt the Turkes.</p>
               <p>There is both in this kingdome and other places ſuch plentie of grapes, that we doubt whether we ſhall be able to get veſſels enough to bring the wine in the ſellers<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:17440:3"/>
               <head>From <hi>Frankford</hi> the 8. of October.</head>
               <p>We haue here tydings receiued how that the Duke of <hi>Baueria</hi> hath denied for weightie reaſons to ſend ſuch ayde to the Infanta at Bruſſels as ſhee deſired to haue of him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>From <hi>Cullen</hi> the 14. of October.</head>
               <p>In many parts of Germany are now ſouldiers leaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for Spaine. The three Regiments of the Baron of Anholt are not as yet diſmiſt for want of pay.</p>
               <p>They write from Mentz that there are dayly many ſouldiers leauied for Spaine by the ſound of the Drum.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>From <hi>Venice</hi> the 1. of October.</head>
               <p>There are three Gallies gone from Genu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to fetch money in Spaine for the Spaniſh Ambaſſadour and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o leauie men for the State of Millaine. And we haue tydings out of France how that the king is there ſtill increaſing his warlike troupes.</p>
               <p>They write out of Switzerland, that the thirteene Cantons were met at Solothorn to make a firme reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution vpon the propoſition made by the French Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour for the recouerie of the Griſons and Valto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lina.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:17440:4"/>
               <head>From <hi>Vienna</hi> the firſt of October.</head>
               <p>The 14. of this moneth, departed two of the Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall Commiſſioners hence, going towards Offen, and the Count of Altheyn who is chiefe Commiſſioner, followed them on the 17. of the ſame Moneth. The Barke which caried the Count was very ſtately ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and painted with red, white, black, and yellow colours: the two other Commiſſioners that went before him are two Barons: namely, the Baron Marn-Weckh, and the Baron Galler. On the Barke of the Count were diuers colours diſplayed, with the Armes and Motto of the order of Knighthood, which is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>Militia chriſtiana.</hi> The ſouldiers which attend v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the Count are all in a liuely, (which he hath giuen vnto them,) and couered with red cloth, with a greene lace vpon it. The Commiſſioners which are appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for Hungary to conclude the peace, are the Count Eſter Haſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Gouernor of Newhenſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l, the Count Frangipan (who is one of the Imperiall Councell of warre, and the Lord S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>sky, beſides ſome othe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. God graunt that this trea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ie of Peace may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>end to the propagation of his holy name, and to the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall good of all Chriſtendome. But they write out of Hungarie, that the Turkes are ſtill verie proud and obſtinate, and haue yet lately ſlaine ſome Imperiall horſe, which were vnder the commaund of the Lord Forgatſch, and lay in a market towne which the Turkes pillaged, and fired, after they had taken thence a good bootie, and many poore chriſtian ſoules which they caried afterwards with them. Some are here of opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that they haue done it by reaſon that they know
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:17440:4"/> that our ſouldiers which lye in Hungarie, may not meddle or skirmiſh with them, being bound to the contrary: or otherwiſe that they thinke to make vs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid, thereby hoping by ſuch meanes to obtaine with more ſpeed that which they deſire.</p>
               <p>And it is againe confirmed from Offen, that the Turkes will not diſmiſſe our Embaſſadour, the Lord Curth who is there, vnleſſe wee reſtore firſt the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, which ſome Imperiall ſouldiers tooke from them, when they were carying it to make payment to the Turkiſh garriſons.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bethlem Gabor</hi> is (as they write out of Hungarie) reſolued to goe in perſon to Offen, and maketh great haſt that he may bee there at the beginning of the Treatie.</p>
               <p>The Lord Staniſlaus Turzo, who is Palatine of Hungarie, is very ſick and likelie to die.</p>
               <p>The taxation which is here made in regard of warres, commodities and labours, is yet verie ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly kept, and there was lately one of the wine preſſers ſtreiked at the Croſſe becauſe he ſaid, that hee would rather forſake the countrey, then labour for ſo litle mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, as is allowed vnto them of his profeſſion by the afore mentioned taxation.</p>
               <p>The Proteſtant ſtates of Auſtria, perceiuing that the Magiſtrats of this citie proceedeth very rigorouſly with the Proteſtants, (who were gone as they were v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:17440:5"/> to their diuine ſeruice, not regarding the Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation by the Burrough maiſter, and Aldermen of the citie made,) and had already ſome puniſhed of them, which they had arreſted and put in priſon, they ſent ſome Commiſſioners to the Emperour to beſeech his Imperiall Maieſtie, that hee would be pleaſed to giue order that the Proclamation afore mentioned might be called back againe: They haue not as yet receiued their anſwer, but it is generally thought that the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour will not hinder the Proclamation or the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of the Magiſtrate.</p>
               <p>To day there were ſome twenty ſix houſes, which ſtand ouer the pull-bridge, tranſported to the Iewes for a ſumme of one and thitrie thouſand florins in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die money, and they are to goe to them on the next Thurſday, vnleſſe ſome alteration happen in the meane time. The Burgers which dwelled there before may there remaine ſtill, but the companie of ſouldiers is to be inquartered in this citie.</p>
               <p>The Emperour is yet at Ebersdorf, and as wee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand he is not likely to remoue thence before Saint Martins day.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>From <hi>Vienna</hi> the 22. of October.</head>
               <p>Some fiue daies agoe departed hence the Count of Altheyn going towards Offen about the treatie of Peace with the Grand Seignior.</p>
               <p>Here are lately ſome Commiſſioners appointed to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:17440:5"/> gather almes to redeeme the poore Chriſtians, which are made ſlaues by the Turks, and Tartars.</p>
               <p>There are here lately many perſons, both called in queſtion and arreſted, for going to the exerciſe of the Proteſtant preachers, againſt the proclamation of the Magiſtrate of this city; the moſt part of them are wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and muſt pay great ſummes of money: there are yet two hundred to come in, beſides them which are already queſtioned.</p>
               <p>The fourteenth of this Moneth cauſed the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners of the countrie, both for themſelues, and in the name of the Proteſtant States, an inſinuation to be made to the Magiſtrate of this citie, to giue them ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to vnderſtand, how they diſlike both their Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation and proceedings, and ſent moreouer on the fifteenth of this moneth two Lords to his Imperiall Maieſtie: namely, the Lord <hi>Ferdinand</hi> of Herberſtein, and <hi>Chriſtopher Leiſir,</hi> to complaine about the procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of the Magiſtrate, and to requeſt his Maieſtie that he would ſtay ſuch ſutes, and maintaine them of the Proteſtant treligion according to his word and promiſe, and ſent thereby a ſhort petition to receiue thereupon his Maieſties gratious anſwer.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>From <hi>Amſterdam</hi> the 19. of October.</head>
               <p>They write out of Spaine that the King hath char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged all Officers of his Kingdomes of Spaine, ſeeing that he can hardly get Mariners <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>now to ſend to the Bay of Todos los Santos, that they ſhould keepe all
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:17440:6"/> the ſouldiers together which ſhall come with the fleet of Noua Hiſpania. And that hee hath written to the Infanta at Bruſſels, that ſeeing the Hollanders do trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble him in ſeuerall parts by water, that ſhe muſt for a time maintaine the warres in the Low-Countries, with the aid of the Subiects which liue vnder her command.</p>
               <p>The kingdome of Portugall is likely to decay, ſeeing that the Marchants loſe dayly many of their ſhips, and that they want the traffike which they had in Bruſſels.</p>
               <p>There goe likewiſe dayly many Mariners of Biſcay to Mariſibia and Rochell, for feare that they might be preſt to goe to the Bay of Todos de la Santos.</p>
               <p>We vnderſtand that the King of France, beſides di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers other Princes and Potentates is to contribute a great ſumme of money to the raiſing of a great Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie.</p>
               <p>The king of Denmarke is with ſome ſhips gone to Gotland to treat about matters of great importance, either with the king of Sweden, or with ſome of his Commiſſioners: but many are of opinion that they are to meet there both in perſon.</p>
               <p>The Marqueſſe <hi>Spinola</hi> receiues yet dayly more men in his Campe, ſeeing that many are run away, and (as it is rumored) the fourth part of them which came in his Campe, forſaken it: and his horſe begins now like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to forſake it, ſeeing that there is great dearth and little money ſtirring: Hee is likewiſe raiſing ſome bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries at ter Heyden, with an intention to hinder the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:17440:6"/> approching of the Prince of Orange.</p>
               <p>They of Breda keepe themſelues very quiet, according to the order giuen by the Prince of Orange, and keepe in the meane time ſtrong watches: and the Gouernor and the other chiefe Commanders ſit many times in Councell vpon the affaires of the Townes. Both the towneſmen and ſouldiers are ſtill of a good carriage, and long mightily to get leaue that they may ſet vpon the enemies.</p>
               <p>Our horſe lately ſurpriſed a Poſt of the Marqueſſe <hi>Spinola,</hi> who was ſent to the Infanta at Bruſſels by him, to giue her Highneſſe to vnderſtand that he muſt haue money with all ſpeed, or that he was not able to keepe the ſouldiers in his Campe.</p>
               <p>By reaſon of the boyſterous winde that blew vpon the twelfth day of October, the waters grew very high in the Low-Countries, and they haue done great hurt about Geertreydenbergh, for there were drowned ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Beaſts, and the violence of the water carried ſome bridges away, which ſtood without the Towne, and drowned alſo ſome of our workes about the Campe of the Marqueſſe <hi>Spinola.</hi> But the Prince of Orange is now daily approaching the quarter of the Enemies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Tetteringen, and conſults many times with his Brother the Duke of <hi>Brunſwick,</hi> and other chiefe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders and skilful Ingeners, how they may annoy the Enemy.</p>
               <p>And we haue receiued tidings that the Count <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> of Naſſaw is ſent with 8000 Foote, and two thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand horſe towards Roſendael to fortifie that place, and to wait vpon the conuoyes of the enemies.</p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:17440:7"/>
               <p>The Count Ernſt of Naſſaw was lately very ſick but God be thanked is now at the mending hand.</p>
               <p>There are dayly many Materials, Fago<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, and great ſtore of Ordinance, Victuals, and Munition, brought to our camp, and it is thought that there ſhall ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſome great enterpriſe bee made by the Prince of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range.</p>
               <p>His Excellency afore mentioned is raiſing two Forts neere the high way, called the long ſtreet, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent that no victuals out of the Dominions of the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Prouinces be any more brought to the enemie, by ſome couetous perſons as hath bin done before.</p>
               <p>The enemies comming lately at Ooſterhout, pilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the village, and tooke all what they could get of the poore countrie people.</p>
               <p>We expect here dayly, many ſouldiers which are diſmiſt by the Kings of Sweden and Denmarke, and lie now about Hamburrough, and tarrie there onely for their chiefe commanders, which are to canduct them into theſe vnited Prouinces. And it is rumord that Count Mansfield, and the Duke chriſtian of Brunſwyck, are likewiſe to get ſome of them vnder their command to imploy them elſe where.</p>
               <p>On Thurſday laſt was the gouernour of the Baye, of of <hi>Todos los Sanctos</hi> with his ſonne, ſome Ieſuits and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther priſoners brought to the houſe of the Weſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia companie at Amſterdam.</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:17440:7"/>
               <p>They write out of Spaine, that the Friggers haue vndertaken, to ſend into the Low-Countries by letters of exchange, the ſumme of ſix hundred thouſand Crownes, for the vſe of the Marqueſſe <hi>Spinola.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Out of the Campe of the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> at <hi>Made</hi> on the 18. of October.</head>
               <p>There came yet dayly many Italians Albaneſe, and other Nations in our camp, hauing forſaken the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe <hi>Spinola,</hi> (as they ſay) by reaſon of the great dearth, and the ſmall pay which is in his Camp.</p>
               <p>They report, how that the Marqueſſe <hi>Spinola</hi> got yet lately foure Regiments in his camp nam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly, two of Wallons, one of Italians, and one of Germains, beſides ſome troups of Horſe. And they are of opinion that the Marques <hi>Spin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>la</hi> wil not be able to lie long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Breda,</hi> ſeeing that the waies grow ſo deep, that the Victuals can not bee caried to the camp, without great difficultie, and that there is almoſt no mony ſtirring in the camp: And they ſay, that euery ſouldier gets no more then fifteene ſtiuers a weeke, which they can eaſily beſtow vpon three pound of bread, and one pound of cheeſe.</p>
               <p>The horſe which came with the laſt conuoy to their camp, were not able to ride vpon their horſes, ſeeing they went ſo deep in the mire, but were compelled to goe a foote, and lead them by the bridle. And they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port moreouer that the Marqueſſe <hi>Spinola,</hi> hearing that the Prince of Orange hath giuen order to ſome Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:17440:8"/> to meet with his conuoy: had giuen directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that no conuoy ſhould any more goe or come without eight thouſand foote, two thouſand horſe, and ſome pieces of Ordinance. But the way is growne ſo deep (as they ſay) that the horſe go in ſome places vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lies in the water, that they will hardly bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to march.</p>
               <p>The Marqueſſe <hi>Spinola</hi> is dayly viewing his campe: and ſtrengthned lately his Quarter of Tettering, with ſom ſouldiers which he took out of the other quarters, and planted there nine peeces of Ordnance vpon a batterie, to hinder the approaches of the prince of Orange with his forces, ſeeing that he drew dayly nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer and neerer to that Quarter.</p>
               <p>A muſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ering being lately made in the Camp of the Marqueſſe <hi>Spinola,</hi> it was found out that there wanted twelue thouſand of the ſouldiers, which were come to his Camp, many of them being runne away, and the reſt ſlayne or deceaſed.</p>
               <p>Yeſterday there came yet ſome perſons out of the towne of <hi>Breda,</hi> and brought letters with them of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall Commanders and Captaines, which relate that there is no difficulty within the Towne: and that all manner of Victuals are there very good cheap, for as they write the Quarter of Corne coſt there but fiue Gilders, the Kan of the beſt beere two ſtyuers, the Kan of their beere of three Gilders the Barrell<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> one ſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, a pound of Butter, fix ſtyuers, a pound of Bakon, fiue ſtyuers, a pound of Cheeſe, three ſtyuers, a pound
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:17440:8"/> of freſh fleſh, foure ſtyuers, and all other things are ſold accordingly.</p>
               <p>They which came out of the Towne, told likewiſe that there were yet a thouſand ſix hundred Oxen and Kyne kept within it in ſeuerall ſtables, and it was thought to bee prouided yet for a yeare and a halfe. Concerning the plague there are none almoſt ſick of it in the Towne: And there were at the ſame time yet ſeuen thouſand reſolute ſouldiers within the towne and the outworkes.</p>
               <p>Wee haue receiued from ſeuerall places tydings, how that our enterpriſe vpon the Caſtle of Antwerps tooke no effect: by reaſon of a horſe of our men, which made ſuch a great noyſe, that a Sentinell of the Caſtle looked thereupon ouer the walles of it, and diſcouered our men which came about it. The Droſt of Borchem who was the chiefe conductor of this enterpriſe mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched on the twelf day of this moneth of October, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout foure of the clock very early in the morning out of the Towne of <hi>Bergen vp Zoome,</hi> with a thouſand foote and foure troupes of horſe, and came about ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen of the clock in the night time before the Caſtle, and had before twelue of the clocke laid ſome of their floates or bridges on the water, which runneth about the Caſtle, faſtened ſome Petards, and erected ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall ladders againſt the walles, and were likely to ſpeed well, if they had not beene diſcouered by the meanes of the afore mentioned horſe.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:17440:9"/>
               <p>There comes yet dayly many Troupes of Horſe and foote in our Camp, and on the thirteenth of this Moneth arriued there the Regiments of Frize-land, beſides diuers other Companies which came from Gerchum, B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mmel, Tiel, and out of ſome Townes of Gelderland; and were preſently inquartered cloſe vnder the trenches of the enemies at Tetteringen.</p>
               <p>The Commander <hi>Smeltſing,</hi> is ſent with fifteene Troupes of Horſe and ſome foote, to make an enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe vpon the enemies.</p>
               <p>They which came out of the Spaniſh Camp, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late how that the Marqueſſe <hi>Spinola</hi> hath told, that although hee was compelled to raiſe his ſiege before <hi>Berghen vp Zoome,</hi> notwithſtanding he had vſed great violence againſt the Towne: he thought to get <hi>Breda</hi> without vſing of any violence.</p>
               <p>And they ſay likewiſe, that hee is yet leauying for the ſeruice of the King of Spaine many Regiments, both in Germany and in the Low-Countries, with an intention to accompliſh the laſt reſolution which was taken at Bruſſels by the Spaniſh Councell of Warre; namely, to raiſe yet another Armie, and to threaten the vnited Prouinces, both by the ſword and fire.</p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:17440:9"/>
               <p>On the other ſide wee heare that the generall States of the vnited Prouinces haue concluded to bring yet another Armie in the field, which is to bee as ſtrong as that which they haue now in the field, to raiſe the Spaniſh Campe before <hi>Breda</hi> which are now, as they ſay, come out of it, euen ten thouſand horſe and thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie thouſand foote. And it is certaine that there are already many chiefe Commanders and Captaines ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to leauy both horſe and foote, and that there are ſome thouſands of ſouldiers which haue ſerued the Kings of Sweden and Denmarke dayly lookt for to come by water in theſe vnited Prouinces.</p>
               <p>By the laſt letters which came from Paris they cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie vs againe that the King of France is ſtill reſolued with the ayde of his confederates, to raiſe ſuch Armies as hath beene concluded vpon.</p>
               <p>And they report, that it is certaine, that the afore mentioned King hath furniſhed Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, with great ſummes of money, to leauie an Army whereſoeuer hee will.</p>
               <p>And they ſay, that the Colonell <hi>Smith</hi> is now lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uying at Sedan two thouſand fouldiers for the ſame
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:17440:10"/> Count, and the Captaine <hi>Daniel de la Riue:</hi> likewiſe a thouſand fiue hundred horſe: So that there is no doubt more to bee made of the raiſing of the Armie of <hi>Count Mansfield:</hi> But the time will learne where it ſhall be imployed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>The foure ſhips which arriued here lately, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming from the Bay of <hi>Todos los Sanctos,</hi> brought with them theſe following priſoners and priſes: namely,</p>
               <list>
                  <item>The Vice-Roy.</item>
                  <item>His Sonne.</item>
                  <item>The Prouinciall of the Ieſuites.</item>
                  <item>14. Other Clergie men.</item>
                  <item>A Sergeant Maior.</item>
                  <item>2516. Cheſts with Sugar.</item>
                  <item>35. Barrels with Sugar.</item>
                  <item>20. Cheſts with leafe Tobacco.</item>
                  <item>1. Cheſt with Tobacco, in rowles.</item>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:17440:10"/>
                  <item>24. Small Barrels with confited Ginger.</item>
                  <item>128. Barrels with Sirupe.</item>
                  <item>125. Pipes with Spaniſh wine.</item>
                  <item>5. Veſſels with Tobacco.</item>
                  <item>59. Teeth of Oliphants.</item>
                  <item>1182. Pieces of Braſil-Wood.</item>
                  <item>4525. Oxen Hides.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:17440:11"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
